Guide to the Witold Gombrowicz Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1944-1970, n.d.; Series I; 5.01; (12 boxes)
  - Tagliaferri, Aldo
    See: Feltrinelli editore, box 3, folder 99
  - Tardos, Tibor, 1969 Feb 2 (Box 11, Folder 397)
  - Tarn, Adam, 1969 Apr 8 (Box 11, Folder 398)
  - Tarnawski, Wit, 1960-69, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 399)
  - Teatro Stabile dell'Aquila, 1969-70 (Box 11, Folder 400)
    See also: Société des auteurs et compositeurs dramatiques (France), box 10, folder 381
  - Technische Universität Berlin, 1961-66 (Box 11, Folder 401)
    Contains correspondence with Walter Höllerer
  - Theater am Neumarkt (Zürich, Switzerland), 1967-68 (Box 11, Folder 402)
  - Théâtre de Bourgogne, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 403)
    Includes WG's notes containing text of telegrams to Jacques Fornier and Maurice Nadeau
  - Théâtre de l'Etuve, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 404)
    Includes a theater poster.
  - Théâtre de Lutece, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 405)
  - Théâtre Montparnasse, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 406)
  - Théâtre National de Chaillot, 1969-70 (Box 11, Folder 407)
    Includes RG's correspondence, list of persons invited to the premiere of Opérette ( Operetka ), a letter written after the premiere by Geneviève Serreau and other persons (unidentified)
  - Thiele, Rolf, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 408)
    Includes a letter from RT's agent
  - Tiel, Walter
    See: Richter, Rudolf, box 9, folder 330-331
  - Times Literary Supplement, 1969, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 409)
    Includes: RG's correspondence; letter to Jerzy Giedroyc
  - Tomeu, Humberto Rodriguez, 1959-67 (Box 11, Folder 410)
  - Torres, Juan Manuel, 1967-68 (Box 11, Folder 411)
  - Tuzinkiewicz, Stanislaw, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 412)
  - Tymieniecki Kazimierz, 1966 Jan 20 (Box 11, Folder 413)
  - Tyrmand, Leopold, 1969, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 414)
  - Union Générale d'Éditions, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 415)
  - Universidad Veracruzana
    See: Sergio Pitol, box 8, folder 302
    See: Cuadernos para el Diálogo, box 3, folder 71
  - Upsala Stadsteater
    See: Norbert Zaba, box 11, folder 432
  - "V" general, 1957-68 (Box 11, Folder 416)
  - Verspoor, Dolf, 1964 Feb 12 (Box 11, Folder 417)
  - Viking Press, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 418)
  - Visión (Revista Latino americana de noticias), 1968 Jan 19 (Box 11, Folder 419)
  - Volle, Jacques, 1967-69, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 420)
  - "W" general, 1958-68 (Box 11, Folder 421)
  - Wasiutynski, Wojciech
    See: Radio Free Europe, box 9, folder 320-321
  - Weidlé, W.
  - Welt, 1966 Jan 2 (Box 11, Folder 422)
  - Werner Söderström Osakeyhtiö, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 423)
  - Weverbergh, Louis Julien, 1964, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 424)
  - Wiadomosci, 1961-69 (Box 11, Folder 425)
  - Wiener Hefte, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 426)
  - Wieniewska, Celina, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 427)
  - Wierzynski, Kazimierz, 1958-60 (Box 11, Folder 428)
    Includes a letter from KW to Alicja de Barcza.
  - Wittlin, Józef, 19[51]-62 (Box 11, Folder 429-430)
    See also: Series V. Writings of Others about Gombrowicz, "Listy Witolda Gombrowicza do Józefa Wittlina", box 35, folder 1032
  - Yale University
    See: Jacques Ehrmann, box 3, folder 94
  - "Z" general, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 431)
  - Zaba, Norbert, 1966-69 (Box 11, Folder 432)
    Includes NZ's Polish translations of reviews from newspapers in Sweden (enclosures), the list of persons in Sweden who were sent WG's books
  - Zachwatowicz, Krystyna, 1951 Aug 24 (Box 11, Folder 433)
    See also: Koukou Chanska, box 6, folder 207
    See also: Series V. Writings by Others About Gombrowicz, Working file (photocopies of letters to WG, dated 1950-67) box 35, folder 1019
  - Zawieyski, Jerzy, 1961 Jun 20 (Box 11, Folder 434)
  - Zdziechowski, Pawel, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 435)
    Includes a note by RG
  - Zielinska, Ludmila, 1953-54 (Box 11, Folder 436)
    Includes a letter from LZ to Kultura
  - Ziemianowska, Zofia, 1953-56, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 437-438)
  - Zwiazek Autorow i Kompozytorow "ZAIKS", n.d. (Box 11, Folder 439)
    Contains a draft of the letter to ZAIKS, on the verso a draft of the authorization for Jorge Lavelli addressed to Société des Auteurs et Compositeurs Dramatiques
    See also: Janusz Gombrowicz, box 4, folder 132
  - Unidentified (French and German), 1961-69, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 440)
  - Unidentified (Polish), 1948-69, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 441)
  - Unidentified (Spanish), 1949-69, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 442)
- Writings of Gombrowicz, 1944-1997; Series II; 3.96; (10 boxes)
  Series II is organized into five subseries: Novels, Plays, Shorter Works, Autobiographical Writings, and Other Writings. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by the title of the work.
  - NOVELS
    - Ferdydurke
      - "Ferdydurke" [fragment published in Skamander 1935, v. 60, different from final redaction], printed version (photocopy) (Box 12, Folder 443)
      - "Skazic urok nowoczesnej pensjonarki!" [fragment published in Studio 1936, Nr 2], printed version (photocopy), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 444)
      - "Kronika Ferdydurke" [notes about the reception of Ferdydurke ], holograph, 1947 (Box 12, Folder 445)
      - "Filibert dzieckiem podszyty" [fragment of Ferdydurke ], newspaper clipping from Nowa Wies, 1975 Sep 21 (Box 12, Folder 446)
      - "Filidor dzieckiem podszyty" [fragment of Ferdydurke ], photocopy of newspaper clipping from 1944 Apr), n.d.
      - Publicity material (?) related to the Spanish edition, in Spanish, typescript carbon, [ca. 1964] (Box 12, Folder 447)
      - Publicity material in Polish, typescript carbon, typescript annotated (photocopy), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 448)
        Includes articles "Jak czytaja Gombrowicza w kraju ( Ferdydurke i Dziennik ," "Krotka historia Ferdydurke," and note by RG
      - Publicity material in French, typescript, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 449)
        Includes text for the cover, articles "Comment Ferdydurke fut interprété par la critique polonaise et française" and "Histoire de Ferdydurke "
      - French translation by Georges Sédir
        - Typescript carbon corrected, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 450-451)
        - Empty original cover (Box 12, Folder 452)
      - Excerpts from the reviews and notes in German and Swiss press, transcript, typescript and typescript carbon (Box 12, Folder 453)
        Includes Polish and Spanish translations
    - Kosmos
      - 1st version [written between 1961 Feb and 1963 Apr in Argentina], holograph corrected, typescript carbon corrected, [1961-63] (Box 12, Folder 454-462)
        Includes drafts of letters on verso, including draft of a letter to Maurice Nadeau (folder 4)
      - 2nd version, typescript, typescript corrected, [1963 May] (Box 13, Folder 463-465)
      - 3rd version, [written in Argentina corrected and augmented in Berlin], typescript corrected, typescript carbon corrected, holograph corrected (by WG and third party), [1964 Dec] (Box 13, Folder 466-473)
      - 4th Version
        - Typescript, uncorrected, [1964] (Box 13, Folder 474)
          Contains pp. 141-151, 158-164 and 166
        - Typescript carbon corrected, holograph, [1964] (Box 13, Folder 475-480)
      - 5th version [written probably in Vence]
        Contains additions to the preceding version (drafts of beginning and end)
        - Holograph, [1964] (Box 13, Folder 481)
        - Typescript corrected, holograph, [1964] (Box 13, Folder 482)
        - Corrected proofs, [1964] (Box 13, Folder 483)
      - Text for the cover (Polish), typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 484)
        Includes notes by RG
      - Corrections to the French translation, typescript annotated, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 485)
    - Opetani
      - De beheksten [fragments of Dutch translation], newspaper clippings, 1981 Sep-Oct (Box 14, Folder 486)
      - Les envoûtés [French language version]
        - [Newspaper serialization], newspaper clippings from Le Monde, 1977 Jul-Sep
        - Dustjacket for the first edition, [1977] (Box 14, Folder 487)
    - Pornografia
      - Fragment, holograph, 1957 Aug 11 (Box 14, Folder 488)
        On the verso notes about articles in the Polish press; accompanied by a scrap of paper containing names and addresses; accompanied by note by RG
      - Draft of a blurb for a German edition, in Polish, holograph, [ca. 1963] (Box 14, Folder 489)
      - Draft of a blurb for an Italian edition, in French, typescript carbon, [1968] (Box 14, Folder 490)
      - List of persons in Argentina who were to receive author copies, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 491)
    - Trans-Atlantyk
      - "El Trans-Atlantico y nuestra crisis literara" [by WG?] typescript carbon, [1953?] (Box 14, Folder 492)
      - Letter to Rudolf Richter including blurb for German edition, 1964 Jun 29 (Box 14, Folder 493)
        With French translation
      - Text of preface with a letter to Halina Grodzicka and Krzysztof Grodzicki, typescript, holograph (photocopy) (Box 14, Folder 494)
      - French translation, fragment, holograph corrected, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 495)
        With a note by RG
      - French translation by Koukou Chanska and François Marié (several chapters,) typescript, corrected (Box 14, Folder 496-497)
        Acccompanied by letter from François Marié
      - French translation by Koukou Chanska and François Marié (complete novel), typescript carbon, corrected (Box 14, Folder 498)
  - PLAYS
    - Historia
      First version of Operetka. First published: Kultura 1975 no. 10
      - Drafts, holograph (in ink and pencil), 1950-51 (Box 14, Folder 499-500)
      - L'Histoire, French translation by Constantin Jelenski
        - Typescript corrected (photocopy), n.d. (Box 14, Folder 501)
        - Printed version (photocopy), n.d. (Box 14, Folder 502)
    - Iwona, ksiezniczka Burgunda
      - Fragments of performance reviews, notes, holograph (photocopy), annotated by RG, [ca. 1966] (Box 14, Folder 503)
      - "Kronika kulturalna" [overview of reviews on performance in Sweden based on materials sent by Radio Free Europe], typescript corrected, [1965-66] (Box 14, Folder 504)
    - Operetka
      - [Version I], holograph corrected, 1958-60 (Box 14, Folder 505-508)
        Includes drafts of letters (to Santucho, Giedroyc?, Wiadomosci ) and notes unrelated to the play on verso of some pages
      - [Version II] typescript corrected (1 page manuscript), [1958-59] (Box 15, Folder 509)
      - [Version III]
        - Basic ideas and early redaction of outlines of the play, [1964-66] (Box 15, Folder 510-512)
        - 1st act and early redaction of 2nd act, holograph corrected, [1964-66] (Box 15, Folder 513-519)
          Includes drafts of outlines of the play and fragments of 1st and 2nd act
        - 2nd act, later redaction, variants, holograph, [1964-66] (Box 15, Folder 520-525)
        - 3rd act, later redaction, variants, holograph, [1964-66] (Box 15, Folder 526-533)
      - [Version IV], typescript carbon, corrected, [1966] (Box 15, Folder 534)
      - Corrections to the text (Polish), typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 535)
      - Notes and corrections to the French translation, holograph corrected (one page photocopy), [1967] (Box 15, Folder 536)
      - Notes and corrections to the French translation, typescript corrected, [1967] (Box 15, Folder 537-539)
      - List of persons who were to receive author copies, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 540)
    - Slub
      - Preface and commentary for the Spanish edition [ El Casamiento ], in Spanish, printed version (photocopy of material of 1948) (Box 16, Folder 541)
      - Notes and stage directions, typescript carbon (photocopy, 1 page original), [ca. 1968?] (Box 16, Folder 542)
        Accompanied by notes by RG
      - ["W. G. jest dzis jednym z autorow..." (general commentary about Slub ),] typescript carbon, [ca. 1965-68] (Box 16, Folder 543)
        Accompanied by note by RG
      - " Slub Gombrowicza w Paryzu" [overview of reviews of the performance in Paris], typescript, typescript carbon (duplicates), [1964] (Box 16, Folder 544)
        Originally found in Koukou Chanska's file; accompanied by note by RG
      - Overview of reviews of the performance in Milano, typescript, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 545)
      - Overview of German reviews, typescript annotated, holograph, n.d (Box 16, Folder 546)
      - Notes about the reception of Slub, typescript, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 547)
      - Photocopy of first pages of French edition [?], n.d. (Box 16, Folder 548)
  - SHORTER WORKS
    - "33 Schriftsteller nennen ihre literarischen Leitbilder" [reply to Tagesblatt 's question], (photocopy of newspaper clipping from 1960 Dec 25), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 549)
      Accompanied by French translation by Constantin Jelenski, manuscript and typescript
    - "Avertissement de Gombrowicz. Imprimé au dos de l'édition de son théâtre," photocopy of printed version from 1965) (Box 16, Folder 550)
    - "Biesiada u hrabiny Kotlubaj"
      - "A feast at countess Kotlubay's," translation by Anna Krajewska- Wieczorek, computer printout, 1997 Apr (Box 16, Folder 551)
      - "The Banquet at countess Kotlubay's," translation by Wiesiek Powaga, printout, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 552)
      - "Le festin chez la comtesse Fritouilh" translation by Georges Sédir, printed version (photocopy), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 553)
    - "Co wiem o Eichlerze?"
      - Typescript annotated, [1956] (Box 16, Folder 554)
      - Newspaper clipping from Glos Polski, 1956 Jul 13 (Box 16, Folder 555)
    - "Contra los poetas," typescript annotated with note by RG, [1947] (Box 16, Folder 556)
    - "Contre la poésie," newspaper clippings (photocopy), 1981 Nov-Dec (Box 16, Folder 557)
    - "Demagogia w opalach, czyli krótki reportaz z Argentyny," typescript carbon, n.d (Box 16, Folder 558)
    - "Do redakcji Glosu Polskiego " [open letter to the editor], (photocopy of newspaper clipping from 1954 Apr 14), n.d.
    - "El arte y el aburrimento," (photocopy of a newspaper clipping from 1944 Jun 11), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 559)
    - "Geba i twarz," typescript corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 560)
    - "Gombrowicz: An Interview" by Bettina Knapp, drafts, typescript carbon and typescript (photocopy), clippings, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 561)
      Accompanied by correspondence, notes
    - "Gombrowicz, l'homme du 'moi'" [interview by Claude Jannoud], newspaper clipping, [1969 Mar 2] (Box 16, Folder 562)
    - "Hoc opus, hic labor est...," newspaper clipping (photocopy of article from 1955 Mar 11), n.d.
    - "Interview avec Gombrowicz" [about the adaptation of Pornografia for the film], typescript, [1968] (Box 16, Folder 563)
    - Interview by Daniel Albo [on the subject of Sur Dante ], correspondence and drafts of replies, typescript, typescript carbon, holograph, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 564)
    - Interview by Vigilio Piñera for Radio el Mundo
      - Holograph (photocopy), [1947] (Box 16, Folder 565)
      - Typescript carbon, [1947] (Box 16, Folder 566)
    - Interview by Georges Sebbag for Voix off, typescript, [1968 Mar?] (Box 16, Folder 567)
    - Interview for Evergreen, French, typescript corrected, annotated by RG, [1966] (Box 16, Folder 568)
    - "J'étais structuraliste avant tout le monde," Quinzaine Littéraire 1967 May 1-15
      - Drafts in Polish, holograph, [1967] (Box 16, Folder 569)
      - Drafts in French, holograph, [1967] (Box 16, Folder 570)
      - "Gombrowicz structuraliste. (Entretien avec J. M. Tourroutaire)" [variant of the text, in French], typescript carbon corrected, [1967] (Box 16, Folder 571)
    - "Kilka slow na temat 'Arte Moderno'," newspaper clipping (photocopy) with accompanying French translation, 1953 Feb 6
    - ["La pensée moderne..."], typescript corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 572)
    - "La Polonia e il mondo latino," photocopy of printed version from 1945 (Box 16, Folder 573)
    - "List do Ferdydurkistów," typescript corrected with accompanying note by RG, [1947] (Box 16, Folder 574)
    - "List otwarty do Brunona Schulza" [an open letter published in Miesiecznik Literacki Studio ], photocopy of printed version from 1936, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 575)
    - "Na kuchennych schodach," photocopy of newspaper clipping from Skamander [1937] (Box 17, Folder 576)
    - "Niedoszla królowa polska przed sadem" [written under a pen name of Andrzej Frycz]
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 577)
      - "Une reine de Pologne en puissance devant le tribunal" [translation by Constantin Jelenski] typescript (photocopy), [after 1969?] (Box 17, Folder 578)
    - "Nosotros y el estilo," photocopy of newspaper clipping from 1944 Apr, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 579)
    - "Nuestro drama erotico"
      A series of articles published in Viva cien años under a pen name of Jorge Alejandro; with notes by RG and French translations
      - "¿Sera acaso necesario crear un ministerio de asuntos eroticos?", photocopy of newspaper clipping from 1944 Oct 18, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 580)
      - "Ellas quieren ser flores," photocopy of newspaper clipping from 1944 Nov 1, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 581)
      - "¡Vida para las mujeres!", photocopy of newspaper clipping from 1944 Nov 15, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 582)
      - "La decencia femenina," photocopy of newspaper clipping from 1944 Dec 6, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 583)
      - "El hombre sudamericano y su ideal de belleza," photocopy of newspaper clipping from 1945 Jan, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 584)
      - "Ellos son muy mallos," photocopy of newspaper clipping from 1945 Jan 17, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 585)
      - "La reforma erótica," photocopy of newspaper clipping 1945 Feb 21, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 586)
      - French translations of articles and note about the Viva Cien Anos (Box 17, Folder 587)
    - "Nuestro rostro y el rostro de la Gioconda," newspaper clipping, [1944 Aug 13] (Box 17, Folder 588)
    - [Open letter to Mieczyslaw Grydzewski], fragment, typescript, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 589)
      Accompanied by a note by RG
    - "Pamietnik Stefana Czarnieckiego"
      - "Stefan's Czarniecki's Diary," translation [unidentified author], computer printout (photocopy), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 590)
    - ["Participer à des enquêtes..." (reply to the call for submissions)], typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 591)
    - ["Pisalem juz kiedys o tym: bylo nas trzech, Witkiewicz, Bruno Schulz i ja" (article about Stanislaw Ignacy Witkiewicz,] typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 592)
    - "Podróz na daleka pólnoc argentynska," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 593)
    - "Polska w Argentynie," typescript, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 594)
    - [Radio discussion never broadcast], in Polish, typescript corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 595)
    - "Refleksje na marginesie Straszewicza," typescript corrected [includes paragraph excised from a final version], [1952] (Box 17, Folder 596)
    - [Replies to interview questions, French], typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 597)
    - [Reply to Radio Free Europe's question about the best Polish book after the war, Polish], typescript, 1956 Apr 14 (Box 17, Folder 598)
    - [Reply to the call for submissions on the topic of eroticism], holograph (photocopy), transcript, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 599)
    - [Reply to the call for submissions on the topic of Stefan Zeromski, Polish], holograph, [1964] (Box 17, Folder 600)
      - Accompanied by note by RG, [1964]
    - "Rozmowa z Gombrowiczem" [interview by Karol Swieczewski], typescript (transcript?), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 601)
    - Submission to Kultura on the topic "Literatura emigracyjna a kraj," typescript annotated by RG, 1956 Nov 12 (Box 17, Folder 602)
    - "Sukces Zygmunta Grocholskiego w Polsce," photocopy of newspaper clipping from 1958 Dec 3, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 603)
    - "Szczur"
      - Printed version with accompanying note by WG, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 604)
      - "The Rat," translation by Wiesiek Powaga, typescript annotated, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 605)
    - "Tancerz mecenasa Kraykowskiego"
      - "Kraykowski's Dancer," translation by Clifford Bacon, computer printout, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 606)
      - "Attorney Kraykowski's Dancer," translation by Christopher Makosa, computer printout, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 607)
      - Printed version (newspaper clipping from ITD ), 1976 Feb 1
    - "The writer and money"
      - "L'écrivain et l'argent," manuscript corrected, 1969 July 22 (Box 17, Folder 608)
        Text dictated in French to RG with note by RG
      - "L'écrivain et l'argent," typescript corrected, 1969, July (Box 17, Folder 609)
      - "The writer and money," newspaper clipping from Times Literary Supplement, 1969
      - "Författare och pengar," [Swedish translation] newspaper clipping from Aftonbladet, 1973 Jun 1973
    - "U pana Jakuba," newspaper clipping (photocopy of article from 1937), n.d.
    - "Z Argentyny," typescript corrected (photocopy of text from ca. 1948), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 610)
      Written under the pen name Komentator; accompanied by letter and note by RG
  - AUTOBIOGRAPHICAL WRITINGS
    - Autobiographical notes, holograph, pencil, [1950s?] (Box 17, Folder 611)
    - Diario de Río Ceballos, printed version, [clipping from Oceano ], [1944 Dec] (Box 17, Folder 612)
    - Dziennik
      - Fragment about Józef Czapski and Argentinian writers, typescript, carbon, corrected, with accompanying note by RG, [1955?] (Box 17, Folder 613)
      - Fragment about Constantin Jelenski, typescript, with accompanying note by RG, [1956?] (Box 17, Folder 614)
      - Dziennik (1961-66), holograph, [ca. 1961-66] (Box 17, Folder 615-621)
        On the verso notes and drafts including draft of a letter [to Harcourt, Brace & World?]
      - Dziennik (1961-66) [?], [draft of an interview], holograph, [ca. 1962-66?] (Box 17, Folder 622)
        Includes several drafts of letters on the verso, including a letter to Alice ----
      - Dziennik, unidentified fragments, holograph, [before 1963 Apr 8?] (Box 17, Folder 623)
      - Dziennik (1967-69), holograph, [1966?-69] (Box 18, Folder 624-630)
      - Dziennik (1967-69) [?], holograph, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 631)
      - Dziennik (1967-69), holograph [photocopy of 6 pages written in 1969], n.d. (Box 18, Folder 632)
      - Dziennik (1967-69), typescript, typescript carbon, corrected and without corrections (Box 18, Folder 633-637)
      - Berliner Notizen
        [German editon comprising fragments of Dziennik 1964-65 ]
        - "Paris-Berlin Erlebnizen" [draft of a preface?], in Polish, holograph, [1964-69] (Box 18, Folder 638)
        - "Przedmowa" [Preface], in Polish, typescript, [1965] (Box 18, Folder 639)
        - Berliner Notizen, fragment, printed version (photocopy), [1966?] (Box 18, Folder 640)
      - Diario Argentino
        [Edition of Dziennik comprising fragments related to Argentina]
        - Drafts of preface, in Polish, holograph, [ca. 1967-68] (Box 18, Folder 641)
        - "Przedmowa" [preface], in Polish, typescript carbon (2 copies), [ca. 1967-68] (Box 18, Folder 642)
        - Fragment (Spanish translation,) typescript corrected, [ca. 1967-68] (Box 18, Folder 643)
        - "Diario transatlantico," transcript corrected, [ca. 1967-68] (Box 18, Folder 644)
      - "Nota" [text in Spanish about publication of Dziennik 1953-56, with accompanying note by RG], typescript corrected, [ca. 1957] (Box 18, Folder 645)
      - Spanish tramslation of the fragment of Dziennik about city Goya and Alejandro Rússovich, typescript corrected (photocopy) (Box 18, Folder 645a)
      - Transcripts of Radio Free Europe programs featuring WG reading fragments of Dziennik, 1958-59 (Box 18, Folder 646)
      - "Journal parisien" [supposedly a TV scenario,] typescript, [1966-67?] (Box 18, Folder 647)
      - Journal Paris-Berlin
        - Preface in French, typescript corrected, [ca. 1968] (Box 18, Folder 648)
        - Text for the cover, [1967] (Box 18, Folder 649)
      - "18.V.1963, Berlin." [Fragment of the French translation of Dziennik by Jadwiga Kukulczanka], n.d. (Box 18, Folder 650)